# **ENAMUL HOQUE PRINCE**

Gates Computer Science 3B, Room 375 353 Serra Mall, Stanford University CA, USA, 94305-1248

+1 415 702 8198 enamul@cs.stanford.edu https://enamulh.github.io

#### **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

My research focuses on combining information visualization and humancomputer interaction with natural language processing to address the challenges of the information overload problem. In particular, I design and develop both text analysis and interactive visualization techniques to explore a large amount of data.

#### **EDUCATION**

09/2012-05/2017 University of British Columbia (UBC), Canada

PhD in Computer Science Advisor: Giuseppe Carenini

Committee: Tamara Munzner, Raymond Ng, Sheelagh Carpendale (external)

Thesis: Visual text analytics for online conversations

01/2010-01/2012 **Memorial University of Newfoundland (MUN)**, Canada

MSc in Computer Science

Advisors: Orland Hoeber and Minglun Gong

Thesis: Concept-based query expansion and interactive visualization for Web

image search

Chittagong University of Engineering & Technology (CUET), Bangladesh 03/2003-08/2007

BSc in Computer Science & Engineering

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

07/2017- present **Stanford University**, CA, USA

Postdoctoral scholar

Conducting research in the areas of data visualization, HCI, and natural

language processing. Supervisor: Maneesh Agrawala

05/2016-09/2016 Tableau Software, Palo Alto, CA, USA

Research Intern

Developed a natural language interface for interaction with visual analytics

systems [18]

**Qatar Computing Research Institute (QCRI)**, Qatar 01/2016-05/2016

Research Associate

Developed and deployed an intelligent visual interface for supporting the

exploration of community question answering forums [C9, D1]. Developed and evaluated a speech act classifier [C7] in collaboration.

09/2012-01/2016 University of British Columbia, Canada

Research Assistant

Developed visual text analytics for online conversations [J6, J7, C5, C6, C9, W4]

09/2012-04/2013, University of British Columbia, Canada

09/2016-06/2017 *Research Assistant* 

Developed InfoVis systems and ran user studies in the Advanced Tools for User-Adaptive Visualization (ATUAV) project [J5, C4, W2, W3]

01/2010-12/2011 Memorial University of Newfoundland, Canada

Research Assistant

Developed tools and techniques for Web image search [J3, J4, C3, W1]

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

Teaching Assistant, University of British Columbia

Marked assignments and exams, answered questions

Fall 2016, Fall 2015 CPSC 422: Artificial Intelligence 2

Summer 2015 CPSC 213: Introduction to Computer Systems

Teaching Assistant, Memorial University of Newfoundland

Marked assignments and quizzes, answered questions

2010-11(Winter, Fall) CS 1700: Computer Basics

*Lecturer*, **Chittagong University of Engineering and Technology**Designed course outline, delivered lectures, developed assessments

2009 Object Oriented Programming

2008 Computer Basics and Programming

2008 Algorithm Design

2008 Computer Graphics

2008 Fuzzy Logic & Neural Network

#### REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

JOURNAL PAPERS

[J9] Enamul Hoque and Giuseppe Carenini, Interactive topic hierarchy revision for exploring a collection of online conversations, *Journal of Information Visualization*, 2018.

**[J8] Enamul Hoque**, Vidya Setlur, Melanie Tory and Isaac Dykeman, Applying pragmatics principles for interaction with visual analytics, *IEEE Transactions* on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. **IEEE VAST**), 2017 (21.0% acceptance rate).

**[J7] Enamul Hoque** and Giuseppe Carenini, Interactive topic modeling for exploring asynchronous online conversations: design and evaluation of ConVisIT, *ACM Transactions on Interactive Intelligent Systems (TIIS)*, Vol. 6, No. 1, pp. 7:1-7:24, 2016.

**[J6] Enamul Hoque** and Giuseppe Carenini, ConVis: A visual text analytic system for exploring blog conversations, *Journal of Computer Graphics Forum* 

(*Proc. EuroVis*), Vol. 33, No. 3, pp. 221-230, 2014, (22.9% acceptance rate).

[J5] Cristina Conati, Giuseppe Carenini, Enamul Hoque, Ben Steichen and Dereck Toker, Evaluating the impact of user characteristics and different layouts on an interactive visualization for decision making, Journal of Computer Graphics Forum (Proc. EuroVis), Vol. 33, No. 3, pp. 371-380, 2014, (22.9% acceptance rate).

[J4] Enamul Hoque, Orland Hoeber, Minglun Gong, CIDER: Concept-based image diversification, exploration, and retrieval, Journal of Information *Processing & Management (IPM)*, Vol. 49, No 5, pp. 1122-1138, 2013.

[J3] Enamul Hoque, Orland Hoeber, Minglun Gong, Balancing the trade-offs between diversity and precision for Web image search using concept-based query expansion, Journal of Emerging Technologies in Web Intelligence (**IETWI**), Vol. 4, No 1, pp. 26-34, 2012.

[J2] Enamul Hoque, Orland Hoeber, Grant Strong, Minglun Gong, Combining conceptual query expansion and visual search results exploration for Web image retrieval, Journal of Ambient Intelligence and Humanized Computing (JAIHC), Vol. 4, No. 3 pp. 389-400, 2011.

[J1] Gahangir Hossain, Enamul Hoque, M. I. Monir, M. A. Sharif, Automatic stemming and its impact in Bangla information retrieval, Computer Science and Engineering Research Journal (CSERJ), Vol. 5, pp. 17-23, ISSN: 1990-4010, 2008.

# PAPERS

CONFERENCE [C9] Enamul Hoque Shafiq Joty, Lluís Màrquez, and Giuseppe Carenini, CQAVis: Visual text analytics for community question answering, In Proceedings of ACM Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI), pp. 161-172, 2017(23%) acceptance rate).

> [C8] Shafiq Joty and Enamul Hoque, Speech act modeling of written asynchronous conversations with task-specific embeddings and conditional structured models, Proceedings of the 54th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), pp. 1746–1756, 2016 (28% acceptance rate).

[C7] Enamul Hoque and Giuseppe Carenini, MultiConVis: A visual text analytics system for exploring a collection of online conversations, pp. 96-107 In Proceedings of ACM Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI), 2016 (25.9% acceptance rate).

[C6] E Hoque, S. Joty, Lluís Màrquez, Alberto Barrón-Cedeño, Giovanni Martino, Alessandro Moschitti, Preslav Nakov, Salvatore Romeo, and Giuseppe Carenini, An interactive system for exploring community question answering forums, International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING), 2016.

[C5] Enamul Hoque and Giuseppe Carenini, ConVisIT: Interactive topic

modeling for exploring asynchronous online conversations, In *Proceedings of ACM Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI)*, pp. 169-180 2015, (22.9% *acceptance rate*).

**[C4]** Giuseppe Carenini, Cristina Conati, **Enamul Hoque**, Ben Steichen, Dereck Toker, James Enns<sup>1</sup>, Highlighting interventions and user differences: informing adaptive information visualization support, In *Proceedings of The ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), pp. 1835-1844, 2014 (23% acceptance rate).* 

**[C3] Enamul Hoque**, Grant Strong, Orland Hoeber Minglun Gong, Conceptual query expansion and visual search results exploration for Web image retrieval, In *Proceedings of the Atlantic Web Intelligence Conference (AWIC)*, pp. 73-82, 2011.

**[C2]** G. Strong, **Enamul Hoque**, Minglun Gong and Orland Hoeber, Organizing and browsing image search results based on conceptual and visual similarities, In *Proceedings of the International Symposium on Visual Computing*, pp. 481-490, 2010.

**[C1] Enamul Hoque**, Gahangir Hossain, Ali Akbar Dewan, Pijush Debnath, An audible Bangla text entry method in mobile phones with intelligent keypad design, In *Proceedings of the International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT)*, pp.279-284, 2009, (31% acceptance rate).

#### **WORKSHOP PAPERS**

**[W5] Enamul Hoque**, Giuseppe Carenini, Multimedia summary generation from online conversations: Current approaches and future directions (EMNLP Workshop on New Frontiers in Summarization), in conjunction with the EMNLP 2017, Copenhagen, Denmark, 2017.

**[W4] Enamul Hoque**, Giuseppe Carenini and Shafiq Joty, Interactive exploration of asynchronous conversations: Applying a user-centered approach to design a visual text analytic system. In *Proceedings of the Workshop on Interactive Language Learning, Visualization, and Interfaces (ILLVI 2014)*, in conjunction with the ACL-2014, Baltimore, USA.

[W3] Giuseppe Carenini, Cristina Conati, Enamul Hoque, Ben Steichen, User Task adaptation in multimedia presentations. *Proceedings of the Workshop on User-Adaptive Information Visualization (WUAV 2013)*, in conjunction with the 21st conference on User Modeling, Adaptation and Personalization (UMAP 2013), Rome, Italy, June 2013.

**[W2]** Cristina Conati, **Enamul Hoque**, Dereck Toker, Ben Steichen, When to adapt: Detecting user's confusion during visualization processing, *Proceedings of the Workshop on User-Adaptive Information Visualization (WUAV 2013)*, in conjunction with the 21st conference on User Modeling, Adaptation and

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup> Author order is alphabetical except for last author

Personalization (UMAP 2013), Rome, Italy, June 2013.

**[W1] Enamul Hoque**, Orland Hoeber, Minglun Gong, Evaluating the trade-offs between diversity and precision for Web image search using concept-based query expansion, *Proceedings of the Workshop on Intelligent Web Interaction*, in conjunction with the IEEE/WIC/ACM International Conference on Web Intelligence, pp. 130-133, Lyon, France, 2011.

#### POSTERS

**[P1] Enamul Hoque**, Orland Hoeber, Minglun Gong, Concept-based interactive visualization approach to Web image search (refereed poster), In *Conference Compendium of the IEEE Information Visualization*, Providence, RI, USA, 2011.

# STUDENT CONSORTIUM

**[S2] Enamul Hoque,** Visual text analytics for online conversations: Design, evaluation, and applications, In *Companion Publication of the International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces* **(IUI)**, pp. 122-125, 2016.

**[S1] Enamul Hoque,** Visual text analytics for asynchronous online conversations, In *Companion Publication of the International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI)*, pp. 105-108, 2015.

#### **BOOK CHAPTERS**

**[B1]** G. Murray, **Enamul Hoque** and Giuseppe Carenini, Opinion summarization and visualization, in *Sentiment Analysis in Social Networks*, Eds. Pozzi, Fersini, Messina, Liu. Elsevier, 2016.

#### **INVITED TALKS**

- Visual text analytics for exploring and understanding large datasets, *University of Victoria*, Canada, February 2018.
- Visual text analytics for exploring and understanding large datasets, *York University*, Canada, February 2018.
- Visual text analytics for exploring and understanding large datasets, *New Jersey Institute of Technology*, USA, February 2018.
- Visual text analytics for exploring and understanding large datasets, *University of Louisiana at Lafayette*, USA, January 2018.
- Visual text analytics for exploring and understanding large datasets, *Nanyang Technological University*, Singapore, January 2018.
- MultiConVis: A Visual text analytics system for exploring a collection of online conversations, *UBC Laboratory for Computational Intelligence (LCI)* Forum Talk, Vancouver, BC, January 2017.
- Visual text analytics for online conversations, *Department of Linguistics*, Simon Fraser University, Burnaby, BC, January 2017.
- An overview of text visualization techniques, *UBC School of Library*,

- Archival and Information Studies (iSchool), Vancouver, BC, December 2016.
- ConVis: A visual text analytic system for exploring asynchronous online conversations, The Pacific Northwest Regional NLP Workshop (NW-NLP), Microsoft Research, Redmond, April 2014.
- A visual text analytic system for asynchronous conversations, *UBC* Laboratory for Computational Intelligence (LCI) Forum Talk, Vancouver, BC, November 2013.
- Conceptual query expansion and visual search results exploration for Web image retrieval, *Department of Computer Science*, Memorial University of Newfoundland, St. John's, NL, November 2010.

#### STUDENTS MENTORED

- 2017 Dae Hyun, PhD student, Stanford University Rastko Djeric, Undergraduate directed study project, UBC 2013 2013 Kaya Gajos, Undergraduate directed study project, UBC 2009 Kazi Shahadat Hossain, Undergraduate thesis, CUET 2009 Sumon Deb, Undergraduate thesis, CUET
- Priyanka Guha, Undergraduate thesis, CUET 2008 Pijush Debnath, Undergraduate thesis [C1], CUET

#### **AWARDS AND HONORS**

2009

2012-2016 Faculty of science graduate award, University of British Columbia 2015, 2016 Travel awards, IUI Conference 2014 Travel awards, ACL Conference 2012 Dean's doctoral award, Memorial University of Newfoundland (declined) 2012 Visa differential scholarship, University of Calgary (declined) 2012 Best prototype award, Human-computer interaction Graduate course, UBC 2011 Fellow of the school of graduate studies, Memorial University 2010-2011 School of graduate studies award, Memorial University of Newfoundland 2007 University merit Scholarship, Bangladesh 1995-2000 Primary and high school talent-pool scholarship, Government of Bangladesh

#### **PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES**

Program committee	IUI (2015-2018), NAACL-HLT 2018, IJCAI-ECAI 2018
Referee	InfoVis 2017, EuroVis 2017, IUI (2015 – 2018), ACM TIIS 2017, Journal of
	Computational Intelligence, Workshop on Human and Technology 2014
Student volunteer	IUI 2016, ACL 2014, Canadian AI/GI/CRV 2011
Representative	Graduate Student Admission Committee, University of British Columbia, 2016
Vice-President	Bangladesh Student Association, Memorial University of Newfoundland, 2011

Volunteer CS open house program, Memorial University of Newfoundland, 2010

Organizing secretary CUET ICT fête, 2010

Coach Programming teams in national programming contests [2008-09]

#### **AFFILIATION**

Member ACM, IEEE, ACL

#### **LEGAL STATUS**

Permanent resident of Canada

#### **REFERENCES**

## **Giuseppe Carenini**

Associate Professor, Computer Science, University of British Columbia carenini@cs.ubc.ca, ≅ +1 (604) 822-5109

#### **Tamara Munzner**

Professor, Computer Science, University of British Columbia tmm@cs.ubc.ca, ☎ + 1 (604) 827-5200

#### **Maneesh Agrawala**

Professor, Computer Science, Stanford University maneesh@cs.stanford.edu, 🖺 +1 (650) 723-2642

## Vidya Setlur

Staff research scientist, Tableau Software, Palo Alto, CA, USA vsetlur@tableau.com, ≅ +1(650) 382-6203

#### Lluís Màrquez

Principal Scientist, Qatar Computing Research Institute lmarquez@qf.org.qa, +974 33225787

# **Minglun Gong**

Professor, Computer Science, Memorial University of Newfoundland gong@cs.mun.ca, ≅ +1 (709) 864-3589